Guide to the New Museum Library Lucy Lippard Collection, 1962-2005 (Bulk 1977-1995) MSS.169
Fales Library and Special Collections
The New Museum Library Lucy Lippard Collection
1962-2005
1977-1995
Fales Library and Special Collections
Lippard, Lucy R.
New Museum of Contemporary Art (New York, N.Y.)
MSS.169
8.96 Linear Feet
Lucy Lippard (born 1937 in New York City) is an American art critic and curator. The New Museum Library Lucy Lippard Collection comprises mostly paper materials compiled and created by Lippard in the course of working on her book Mixed Blessings: New Art in a Multicultural America, which she later donated to the New Museum Library.
Biographical Note
Lucy Lippard (born 1937 in New York City) is an American art critic and curator. An early champion of conceptual art, feminist artists, and artists of color, Lippard has authored numerous books on art and art theory. She is a co-founder of Printed Matter, an art book and artist's book shop in New York City, and an original member of the Heresies Collective, a group of feminist artists and critics responsible for the journal Heresies: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics. Lippard was educated at Smith College (B.A., 1958) and the Institute of Fine Arts at New York University (M.A. Art History, 1962).
Publications
On the Beaten Track: Tourism, Art and Plac e (1999)
The Lure of the Local: Sense of Place in a Multicentered Society (1997)
Defining Eye: Women Photographers of the 20th Century (1997)
Michael Lucero: Sculpture (1996)
Contact Lenses, Corrected Vision, Nueva Luz photographic journal (1995)
The Pink Glass Swan: Selected Essays on Feminist art (1995)
Partial Recall: Photographs of Native North Americans (ed.) (1992)
A Different War: Vietnam in Art (1990)
Secrets, Dialogues, Revelations: The Art of Betye and Alison Saar (1990)
Mixed Blessings: New Art in a Multicultural America (1990, 2000)
Jerry Kearns (1987)
Get the Message: A Decade of Art for Social Change (1984)
Overlay: Contemporary Art and the Art of Prehistory (1983)
Collected Visions: Work by Women Artists Living in Rural New York State (1982)
Ad Reinhardt (1981)
Intricate Structure (1980)
Issue: Social Strategies by Women Artists (1980)
Sol LeWitt (1978)
From the Center: Feminist Essays on Women's Art (1976)
Eva Hesse (1976)
Six Years: The Dematerialization of the Art Object (1973)
Tony Smith (1972)
I See/You Mean: A Novel (1979)
Changing: Essays in Art criticism (1971)
Dadas on Art (ed.) (1971)
Surrealists on Art (ed.) (1970)
Pop Art (1966)
Graphic Work of Philip Evergood (1966)
Sources
Lucy Lippard. (2010). In Encyclopædia Britannica. Retrieved December 02, 2010, from Encyclopædia Britannica Online: http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/1065408/Lucy-Lippard.
Arrangement
The collection came to the Fales Library with little discernible order. Only the files in series I appeared to have some ordered relation, although the folders themselves were dispersed over many boxes. The folders for series I were collected and arranged alphabetically. All other series were created by the processing archivist for this collection through a thorough examination of the material.
The Collection is described at the box level, and is arranged into eight series:
Series I: Subject Files
Series II: Artist Files
Series III: Correspondence
Series IV: Printed Material
Series V: Will Olander
Series VI: Guest Books
Series VII: New Museum Building
Series VIII: Sound recordings
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Provenance
The collection was transferred to the Fales Library in 2005 from the New Museum of Contemporary Art at the time Fales acquired the New Museum Library's book collection. It consists mostly of materials created and collected by Lucy Lippard while writing her book Mixed Blessings: New Art in a Multicultural America, which she donated to the New Museum Library after the book's publication. When the transfer was made to NYU, some unrelated material from the New Museum Library was transferred as well.
Scope and Content
The New Museum Lucy Lippard Collection comprises mostly paper materials, along with some bound materials and objects. The bulk of the materials was collected and created by Lippard in the course of working on her book Mixed Blessings: New Art in a Multicultural America, and later transferred to the Library of the New Museum of Contemporary Art. Some materials, all of which were transferred to Fales from the New Museum Library, appear to be unrelated to Lippard and her research, but were kept with the collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Lippard Papers were transferred from the New Museum. Most of the materials in that transfer were books from the New Musem Library, but some were Lippard's files. The accession number associated with this donation is 2005.169
Art -- Political aspects.; Ethnic arts.; Invitations.; Press releases.; Art museums -- New York (N.Y.); Dissertations.; Announcements.; Art criticism.; Correspondence.; Lerman, Leo, 1914-1994; Dougherty, Alan; Olander, William; New Museum of Contemporary Art (New York, N.Y.); Lippard, Lucy R.
- Series I: Subject Files, 1962-1995; undated
  Scope and Content
  This series comprises folders created by Lippard on subjects relating to non-Western/cross-cultural art and artists. The series contains some correspondence (mostly postcard announcements), which were left in place to preserve the original order. Some unlabeled folders that appeared to be subject files are labeled "[Unidentified subject file]" and placed near the end of the series.
  Material in this series is arranged alphabetically by folder name.
  - Subject Files, 1975-1989; undated (Box 1)
  - Subject Files, 1977-1993; undated (Box 2)
  - Subject Files, 1962-1995; undated (Box 3)
    General
    Folders 1-19.
- Series II: Artist Files, 1975-1994; undated
  This series comprises folders and binders containing material on specific artists.
  Material in this series is arranged alphabetically by artist name.
  - Artist Files, 1975-1994; undated (Box 3)
    Folders 20-37.
- Series III: Correspondence, 1980-1994; undated
  This series comprises all correspondence in the collection not contained in the Subject Files series. Not all correspondence is to/from Lippard.
  Material in this series is arranged chronologically by earliest date on folder. Some folders contain wide ranges of dates, but material were kept together to preserve original order.
  - Correspondence, 1980-1994; undated (Box 4)
    Folders 1-11.
- Series IV: Printed Material, 1968-1996; undated
  Series comprises miscellaneous printed material found either foldered in unlabeled folders or loose in boxes. Materials are almost exclusively gallery announcements, invitations, press releases, and exhibition catalogs. Series contains some correspondence, mostly postcard announcements, left in place to preserve original order. Some items in this series are stamped "RECEIVED; [date]; LEO LERMAN."
  Material in this series is arranged chronologically by earliest date on folder.
  - Printed Material, 1962-1992; undated (Box 4)
    Folders 12-25.
  - Printed Material, 1984-1992; undated (Box 5)
  - Printed Material, 1991-1996; undated (Box 6)
    Folders 1-16.
- Series V: Will Olander, 1983-1995
  Series contains material created by Will Olander (his dissertation) or concerning his memorial service and a memorial fund in his name.
  Material in this series is arranged chronologically.
  - Will Olander, 1983-1995 (Box 6)
    Folders 17-25.
- Series VI: Guest Books, undated
  Series contains guest books from an unknown exhibition. Each guest book has a question printed on the cover which the messages inside attempt to address.
  - Guest Books, undated (Box 6)
    Folder 26.
  - Guest Books, undated (Box 7)
    Folder 1.
- Series VII: New Museum Building Proposals, 1994; undated
  Series comprises building proposals for the New Museum from varioius architecture firms.
  - New Museum Building Proposals, 1994; undated (Box 7)
    Folders 2-4.
- Series VIII: Sound recordings, 1984; 1994; 1996
  When a media ID number is followed by the letter 'A', it indicates that paper material associated with that item has been separated and stored elsewhere (see Subseries C).
  - Subseries A: Access Copies
  - Subseries B: Originals, 1984; 1994; 1996
    - "When the Bomb Drops" by Peter Pryor; 7" vinyl record w/ Picture Sleeve, 1984; ID: 169.0001 (Box 8, Media ID: 169.0001)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Currently unavailable until duplication occurs.
    - "When the Bomb Drops" by Peter Pryor; 7" vinyl record w/ Picture Sleeve, 1984; ID: 169.0002 (Box 8, Media ID: 169.0002)
    - "That's Art?", May 5, 1986; ID: 169.0003 (Box 8, Media ID: 169.0003)
    - "Replacement Tape; New Museum", January 10, 1994; ID: 169.0004 (Box 8, Media ID: 169.0004)
- Oversize Series I: Subject Files, undated
  Series comprises oversize items from series I.
  Oversize material is arranged by series and chronologically within each series.
  - Subject Files, undated (Box 9)
    Folders 1-3.
- Oversize Series II: Artist Files, 1985; undated
  Series comprises oversize items from series II, namely a binder containing material by and about the artist Red Spot (Alan Dougherty).
  - Artist Files, 1985 (Box 9)
    Folders 4-5.
  - Artist Files, undated (Box 10)
  - Artist Files, undated (Box 11)
- Oversize Series III: Correspondence, undated
  Series comprises oversize items from series III.
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 10)
    Folder 2.
- Oversize Series IV: Printed Material, 1968-2005; undated
  Series comprises oversize items from series IV.
  - Printed Material, 1968-2005; undated (Box 10)
    Folders 3-9.
  - Printed Material, 1999 (Box Shared Fales 080, Folder 6)